[SPEAKER_01]: It might not be clear what it actually means to practice, you know, do something out of faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: As you know, you've been saying a few times recently, especially, that just based on faith, somebody might practice rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter whether they practice based on faith or based on, you know, a ton of, like, reasoning.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the point is that they practice rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what is that faith?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, well, there you go.
[SPEAKER_05]: You just kind of described it there.
[SPEAKER_05]: In order to have faith, you need to know what you're actually supposed to do that is directly related to freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's not other way around.
[SPEAKER_05]: You're not gonna understand what you need to do on account of just blind faith.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'll just do these random things and somehow the way out of suffering will become apparent to me.
[SPEAKER_05]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it's like you need to understand to a degree what needs to be done correctly and then find the motivation to do it either through reasoning or through faith.
[SPEAKER_05]: Let's put it that way.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because then it needs to be applied.
[SPEAKER_05]: The effort needs to be made.
[SPEAKER_05]: So,
[SPEAKER_05]: So, say, somebody understands to a degree, gradual training, what needs to be done, understands that the route of actions is where your intentions are, and all of that, and now he needs to start doing it on a day-to-day basis.
[SPEAKER_05]: And sometimes, he might not be quite clear as to why he should always, like, not act out of sensuality, or why he should always be watchful of intentions, and why he should do this or that, that's within the gradual training, but out of faith, he'll do it.
[SPEAKER_05]: He won't spend much time rehashing why should I do this, what I'm already doing.
[SPEAKER_05]: He'll just stick to doing it, but again, on the right level.
[SPEAKER_05]: But you could see exactly, because there is kind of less discernment in regard to what specifically needs to be done in terms of the correct, right training and practice.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's very easy to then start conflating that, oh, I'll just emulate the external mode of behavior,
[SPEAKER_05]: And not question it, and that's my faith.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that's... well, I guess you can call it a faith, but it's a completely... not a faith that can... that can give rise to satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: The other thing I was thinking about this is this...
[SPEAKER_01]: You can sort of have a particular idea of, okay, like, I have a lot of faith in such and such teacher.
[SPEAKER_01]: It makes a lot of sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: It, you know, really makes sense to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've thought about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now, just kind of, okay, this particular contemplation I was supposed to do, let me just do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's something that you can do out of just a sense of duty or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not really possible to do the same, like to actually just not act out of unwholesome things, be watchful of one's intentions.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's kind of not a particular thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a specific method that you can just follow like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's kind of, I think, the main difference that it's... or one difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the other thing is, I think, even just in order to be able to do that, you already kind of have to be somewhat taking responsibility for your own idea or view of what you think or what you believe should be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, rather than just, oh, so-and-so said or this is what I believe in and let me... And also, like, sometimes if you hear something that does resonate with
[SPEAKER_05]: Your current level of understanding and so on, and you feel inspired, and you feel like you have faith to do what that person says.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, you should also ask yourself and know, like, wait, but what is it that I find inspiring?
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, in hearing this teaching from so-and-so, I feel so inspired.
[SPEAKER_05]: What is the inspiring aspect?
[SPEAKER_05]: What facet of that inspires me?
[SPEAKER_05]: Am I clear?
[SPEAKER_05]: Or do I, like, or I don't know?
[SPEAKER_05]: Or
[SPEAKER_05]: Oh, well, you know, as long as there is an inspiration, I won't question it further.
[SPEAKER_05]: No, you have to.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because you might simply be inspired by the way somebody speaks, and you still haven't understood what he's saying.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Are you inspired by the teacher or the teaching?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: But then again, like, when you say, okay, I'm inspired by the teaching, okay, but are you understanding it correctly, or are you just reading into it what you already think teaching is?
[SPEAKER_05]: And the particular wording of this teacher allows you to put your take on it.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's like...
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you need to study it.
[SPEAKER_05]: You need to study it closer.
[SPEAKER_05]: You need to... That's what we say.
[SPEAKER_05]: It takes time.
[SPEAKER_05]: You need to kind of live with somebody, i.e.
[SPEAKER_05]: you need to actually be exposed to what they're saying for a period of time, to get to know them, to get to see what they say, what they mean, and so on.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because, again, it's just...
[SPEAKER_05]: Words are just...
[SPEAKER_05]: Shells, in terms of, like, externally approach, they're just shells of the meaning.
[SPEAKER_05]: You don't necessarily know what that person meant, because those words, those shells, might not mean the same to you.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, all of that, will already bring a discernment, authenticity and clarity.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, then, even if, even if you don't necessarily find a specific inspiration through a specific teacher, by questioning like this, well, you'll be able to inspire yourself.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because you have the suttas, you have the stuff said, and now you kind of know to not just take it for granted, because you develop that habit of questioning it.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, yeah, then you won't need an external inspiration in order to practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: That was the other thing I wanted to bring up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like a faith often, kind of, the idea of faith, it does often imply faith in a particular, I don't know, guide or teacher or something.
[SPEAKER_05]: Or a method, yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Something palpable, measurable, that I can forget myself, about myself or my responsibility and just do it, just commit to it and do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which it doesn't, obviously, correctly at all.
[SPEAKER_05]: I mean, yeah, you should follow the method of
[SPEAKER_05]: Watching your intentions before every single action you make throughout the day.
[SPEAKER_05]: But how much of a method that is, well, you'll find out.
[SPEAKER_05]: But in a way, yeah, if you need a method, commit to a method of the right kind.
[SPEAKER_05]: But it's not.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's not going to be found on that level, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that, and the reason that that's called faith, that there is an element of faith always, even if you have all of the, you know, even if you're just kind of committing absolutely to your reasoning and needing to understand everything, you still need to have some faith element, because where the work ends up really needing to be done, is on a level where you can't
[SPEAKER_01]: This was to give the example of the other talk recently about enduring things on the right level.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you were talking about seeing them as phenomenon and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you...
[SPEAKER_01]: There was one point, then, that somebody made, that if you were to see it as a phenomenon correctly, that pressure won't be felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't see that end of it when you're starting, just having to kind of learn how to endure it on the right level.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you can't kind of put that result in front of yourself as a kind of a carrot or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to be able to
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's the actual faith aspect.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so you know theoretically, but once you start doing it practically,
[SPEAKER_05]: That theory won't apply.
[SPEAKER_05]: Your ideas of it, when you're pressured, when you have to endure and not act out and practice sense-restraint...
[SPEAKER_05]: So, again, you can then mask that by saying, well, it's my duty, it's my identity, it's my... it's the tradition, it's whatever.
[SPEAKER_05]: Or you cannot fall into that, but then, yes, then you won't have any other confirmation or affirmation that what you're doing is right, and you just stick to it to that extent that you don't know.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because, again, what you're doing is simply refrain... Well, what you're doing is what you know you should be doing, which is refrain from sensuality, not act out.
[SPEAKER_05]: But, obviously, as I said, when those things are actively pressuring you, you kind of
[SPEAKER_05]: You need.
[SPEAKER_05]: There is this need of, okay, give me some affirmation of this, some reassurance that what I'm doing is right.
[SPEAKER_05]: Although, you know that what you're doing is right.
[SPEAKER_05]: You're not acting out of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_05]: That is already right.
[SPEAKER_05]: You might not feel how you wanted to feel, but it is right.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, have faith in that knowledge.
[SPEAKER_05]: Have faith in that instruction and stick to it.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's what faith means.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you realize, really, faith, in terms like saḷā, from the suttas, should be translated as confidence.
[SPEAKER_05]: Not, not faith.
[SPEAKER_05]: I mean, faith is not wrong, once we clarify everything else around it.
[SPEAKER_05]: But, more accurately, it's really confidence.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, I'm confident that what I know I should be doing is the right thing, on account of reasoning, on account of everything else, on account of information, on account of pondering.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, I'm doing it out of that confidence.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it's like, I have confidence in instruction, implies that, to that degree, you have some discernment of the instruction.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, what are you confident about?
[SPEAKER_05]: But if you say, I have faith in instruction, means I just need to surrender to it and my work's done.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, same, I have faith in Jesus or whatever.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's like, no, I have confidence in the teaching.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, well, please explain the extent that you understood it.
[SPEAKER_05]: That gives you confidence.
[SPEAKER_05]: Then, maybe I'll get the same confidence.
[SPEAKER_05]: But, I have faith in it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Ah, well, he's the greatest, he's the best.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, great.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, I approve of that.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, I have faith because he's the greatest, he's the best.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'll be the saved...
[SPEAKER_05]: I'll be saved...
[SPEAKER_05]: I'll be the
[SPEAKER_03]: A reminder of the Sutta.
[SPEAKER_03]: I might read it now.
[SPEAKER_03]: That it's like, even though you understand that renunciation is peaceful, yet you don't do it when it comes to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, you can do it when you're here.
[SPEAKER_05]: You're doing it, doing it, doing it, but when the pressure builds up...
[SPEAKER_03]: You give it up.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Even if I know that it's peaceful, I've reasoned it out to a great extent.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why am I not... Why does my mind launch out towards renunciation?
[SPEAKER_03]: What am I missing?
[SPEAKER_05]: Because you haven't developed confidence in what you already know.
[SPEAKER_05]: You don't have enough faith in it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Or because you haven't given up desire?
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_05]: You haven't given up desire because you haven't given up desire.
[SPEAKER_05]: And you haven't given it up because you don't have enough faith in giving it up.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, the point is, the time will come, as I said, when no amount of your information can do the work for you,
[SPEAKER_05]: And then you have to endure the pressure of desire, and that's where your faith in what you know is measured.
[SPEAKER_05]: I have no reason to not act out of this sensuality.
[SPEAKER_05]: My mind is already made up.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm gonna go.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm gonna take it.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm gonna get it.
[SPEAKER_05]: But I know I shouldn't.
[SPEAKER_05]: Just that, pretty much, remote, abstract, far removed, no weight whatsoever to it, thought of, I shouldn't do it, you have faith in that.
[SPEAKER_05]: Enough, and you won't do it.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, yeah, if you keep breaking the precepts, means you don't have enough faith in not breaking the precepts.
[SPEAKER_05]: That faith won't just magically appear in these thoughts.
[SPEAKER_05]: You need to...
[SPEAKER_05]: So, if you don't have enough faith, you need to build it up.
[SPEAKER_05]: You build it up through developing that confidence.
[SPEAKER_05]: Confidence that this is actually the way out, that this is what I fundamentally want to achieve even through sensuality.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's actually achieved through sense restraint, peace, equilibrium, satisfaction.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, so you're questioning what faith you have.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, you question what faith you have, see if you lack it, and you lack it if, as I say, if you keep acting out, and then actually start making the effort.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, instead of just sitting down and seeking, chasing calmful, pleasant experiences, sit down and keep reviewing, revisiting, and building up that confidence in things that you know you should be doing, and yet you keep failing.
[SPEAKER_05]: You keep failing because you haven't obviously thought it well through.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because if you did, it would have sunken deeper.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that means, when things are like at the toughest point, you would have enough faith, despite of how pressured to act you are, you have enough faith to not act out and just weather the storm.
[SPEAKER_05]: So you don't weather the storm when you don't have faith in what you're doing during that storm.
[SPEAKER_05]: I sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, how do I stop breaking the precepts?
[SPEAKER_05]: That's how you stop breaking the precepts.
[SPEAKER_05]: By constantly reflecting and pondering on the dangers of doing so, on the benefits of not doing so, on everything else that's involved, like your day-to-day actions, the perils of desires, the disruption of peace, all of that.
[SPEAKER_05]: And you will gradually be increasing that faith and being able to not act out more and more.
[SPEAKER_05]: But it's not magically going to happen on account of just practicing calming.
[SPEAKER_05]: Then, when pressure comes, oh, my mind is disrupted now, and everything that that I heard before, and that I know, or even that I understood, has no weight now for the duration of this pressure, and I'll just act out.
[SPEAKER_05]: That time has to come for everyone.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that's where you measure your actual faith.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's... we said that before.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's what, like, somebody... like an actual sotāpāna is not an anāgāmī yet, because he might be lacking faith within, you know, within his great state of faith and confidence.
[SPEAKER_05]: On some specific aspects, he might not have enough faith.
[SPEAKER_05]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_05]: To stick to certain behaviors, they would be taking him away from sensuality further.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, he would review that.
[SPEAKER_05]: He could review that and realize, oh, I lack faith in those crucial little moments of giving in, here and there.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, what if I don't give in and build up my faith through remembering, through recollecting the danger, the peril, the dissatisfaction?
[SPEAKER_05]: It goes every... against everything that I already work for, pretty much, at that point.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, recollect that, ponder on that frequently, as the Buddha would say, and the mind will lean in that direction.
[SPEAKER_05]: But see, people don't ponder on things frequently at all, with that kind of intent, right intent behind it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, they might ponder on something, and then adopt the view on account of it, and that's it, my work's done, and then now give me a calming technique, a practice, sensation watching, a bit of this, a bit of external duty, I just do this because everybody else does, and I shall not be reflecting or pondering or revisiting the stuff again, because that is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_05]: But it's like, no, the practice is frequently recollect.
[SPEAKER_05]: Again, not mechanically go through the words and mantras, but revise, recollect, bring up... Ideas.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_05]: Ideas, contexts, information that you learned before, until the mind actually starts to settle in there.
[SPEAKER_05]: And the more often you do that right type of recollection,
[SPEAKER_05]: The calmer the mind would be, the less disturbed.
[SPEAKER_05]: And same when the Buddha says in the suttas, the householder who has the right view, his samādhi, his pleasant abiding, like jhāna for monks, is when he frequently recollects the Buddha, the dhamma, the saṅgha, the unbroken virtue.
[SPEAKER_05]: Again, not as a blind recital to a golden shrine, but actually recollects the value, the meaning, the point, his involvement, makes it alive through recollection and diligent mental effort.
[SPEAKER_05]: And there and then, he has pleasant abiding there and now.
[SPEAKER_05]: Nothing can touch him.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sati.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_05]: Sati.
[SPEAKER_05]: You can't have too much of recollection.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, if somebody lacks faith, it's because they haven't recollected enough, yeah, haven't dwelt on it long enough, haven't clarified it long enough.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that's... that is the measure, actually.
[SPEAKER_05]: Somebody can be full of faith, but has zero confidence.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, if you were to ask them, if you were to interrogate them and question about the practice, they'll be all over the place and there'll be absolutely no confidence there.
[SPEAKER_05]: They still might be blinded by that faith.
[SPEAKER_05]: They still might not accept what you have to say.
[SPEAKER_05]: But their lack of confidence in their own words will become very apparent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Actually, that's nearly... the more you lack confidence, the more faith you need.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, you need to compensate it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can't see the discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe you have real faith in this teacher, but the teaching is discrepant, or there are these contradictions which you're not seeing.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, nobody doubts that that faith is real as such, but it's misguided.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not authentic.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: Misplaced.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you know, it's just to say, like, the... he has confidence in the instruction, then he applies himself, becomes a sotāpanna, and... sorry, he has faith in the instruction, becomes a sotāpanna, and then he develops confirmed confidence in the teaching.
[SPEAKER_05]: In other words, he saw it for himself, now his confidence has been confirmed.
[SPEAKER_04]: I was gonna say that's then that confirmed faith.
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you could say he has confidence to a degree, but he hasn't confirmed it still thoroughly for himself.
[SPEAKER_05]: And for a sotāpanna, he has confirmed confidence in the teaching that is right, because he actually is free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, there is no greater verification of the truthfulness and the right practice there.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you could say he has faith, that then gets confirmed.
[SPEAKER_05]: But see, when you know now that this works, you don't... there is no belief involved anymore.
[SPEAKER_05]: Now you know.
[SPEAKER_05]: You have confirmed it, that it works, so you don't need to believe it and hope that it works.
[SPEAKER_05]: It works.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, like the sutta of the hen having to sit on its eggs for chicken to lay out, to come out safely.
[SPEAKER_05]: You could say, first time, say, first time hen doesn't necessarily know that if she lays on the eggs, the chicks would come out safely.
[SPEAKER_05]: He has some confidence and some faith that that's how it works.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then it does... it does the work.
[SPEAKER_05]: It sits on the eggs, and the chicks come out safely.
[SPEAKER_05]: Then, for the next time, she won't have to question it again, because she has confirmed that that's what it works.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, in the beginning, for the first time, she might have doubt... had a lot of doubt of, oh, should I get up now?
[SPEAKER_05]: Should I stay?
[SPEAKER_05]: How long should I stay?
[SPEAKER_05]: Should I leave?
[SPEAKER_05]: How quickly I have to return?
[SPEAKER_05]: Maybe this won't work.
[SPEAKER_05]: Maybe I need to leave them alone for them to hatch.
[SPEAKER_05]: Maybe... All of these thoughts would have been passing through its head.
[SPEAKER_05]: But if it actually sat on its eggs
[SPEAKER_05]: So, next time, she won't have the same doubts again, because all she needs to do is just not give in to those doubts, because she knows that what she's doing is already right.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, she doesn't rely on any circumstance for her confidence, that her confidence is independent of any... At that point, afterwards, yes, exactly, exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, nothing can come in between that.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's exactly what it was described in the suttas by that Sotāpanna who said, well, even if the whole world says one thing and the Buddha said the other, the opposite, like, the Buddha's right.
[SPEAKER_05]: Not because he's a fundamentalist, blinded lunatic.
[SPEAKER_05]: No, it's because he actually confirmed that thing for himself.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, nobody can come in between that.
[SPEAKER_05]: If people say the opposite, it's because they haven't seen it for themselves.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it's directly visible here and now.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that is, and that should be the criteria, by the way, even for somebody before they become a sotāpanna and start practicing and so on.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, the goals, the results should be visible here and now.
[SPEAKER_05]: You know.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_05]: It won't happen overnight.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's not an instant thing.
[SPEAKER_05]: You have to sit on the eggs.
[SPEAKER_05]: But, okay, but, you know, I've been doing it for 20 years now.
[SPEAKER_05]: Isn't that a bit long?
[SPEAKER_05]: Where is the right view?
[SPEAKER_05]: I've been following this teaching or that teaching for how long?
[SPEAKER_05]: Two days?
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_05]: Maybe follow a bit longer.
[SPEAKER_05]: Two years?
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_05]: You know.
[SPEAKER_05]: Is there any anything to show for?
[SPEAKER_05]: Five years?
[SPEAKER_05]: Ten years?
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_05]: Come on now.
[SPEAKER_05]: But not like... just dismiss that part of results and still just convince yourself that you're doing it right.
[SPEAKER_05]: No?
[SPEAKER_05]: It should be happening.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, yes, there is a such thing to be a bit impatient, but then there is a such thing to, like, completely disregard the fact that you will not know whether you're doing it rightly until you confirmed it, that it is the right thing to do.
[SPEAKER_05]: In other words, until you know for yourself, until you're a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: It comes down to not really disregard... not disregarding... Not disregarding the goal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your own aim.
[SPEAKER_05]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is my aim?
[SPEAKER_05]: When I have an aim, I do what it takes to get... Now, that aim, obviously, as I said, as you discern more, will become more refined, let's say, let's put it that way, than what it used to be.
[SPEAKER_05]: But fundamentally, you need to keep it in the play.
[SPEAKER_05]: You need to keep it there as a relevant thing.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because you are doing this to be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_05]: Are you free from suffering?
[SPEAKER_05]: Do you know the way out of suffering for yourself, independent of any circumstances, exactly?
[SPEAKER_05]: Can something come in between it?
[SPEAKER_05]: Can something cause doubt that would completely change the course of your effort?
[SPEAKER_05]: Or do you know for yourself, beyond doubt, cannot be shaken, you know exactly, what suffering is and what escape from it is?
[SPEAKER_05]: Exactly, there's nothing that can come in between.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's like the most direct thing you see.
[SPEAKER_05]: And feel, obviously, by that point.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you can kind of apply that
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, way of thinking, even if you don't know for yourself, you can think, well, is my current understanding along the lines that could not be
[SPEAKER_04]: Turned upside down by something or whatever.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, well, kind of find out you can't go into, like, particulars and turn them around to fit.
[SPEAKER_04]: Without changing the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: But kind of to, well, to find where your understanding or misunderstanding does not have that nature of being unable to be, well, yeah, mistaken or turned upside down.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, needs to be, needs to be sound.
[SPEAKER_05]: Needs to be free from contradiction.
[SPEAKER_05]: Free from, eh...
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, you might be emotionally invested in it, and which is why it would be unpleasant to question it, and you're emotionally invested because, you know, freedom from suffering is taken personally, it's important, so that's fine, that's understandable, but that should not prevent you from questioning it.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you need to know
[SPEAKER_05]: That it is a sound thing, that can hold the water, as it said, and, eh... so... and that exactly, it cannot be upturned by... by the opposing view.
[SPEAKER_05]: In other words, you would see opposing view, where the lack... where it lacks, but it doesn't add up, because you thought your view through.
[SPEAKER_05]: You didn't just accept it, took it on, and now, you know, a disagreement comes, or... or... or something that says, oh, well, no, that's wrong, and you... you just... you just go in a defense mode without recognizing, wait, but do I see where this applies?
[SPEAKER_05]: Maybe it's right
[SPEAKER_05]: What if it is right?
[SPEAKER_05]: Do I know that it isn't right?
[SPEAKER_05]: Do I know that I'm right?
[SPEAKER_05]: Or do I just desperately need to believe that I'm right and have to shut everything else out?
[SPEAKER_05]: Even if you're not, if you don't know for yourself yet, you can certainly not find fault or any contradiction in the value of sense restraint and saying no to sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: You'll find a lot of pain in it.
[SPEAKER_05]: But that's not to say that it's not a logically sound conclusion, that it's better to be withdrawn from desires and not act out of them, and not scratching the itch.
[SPEAKER_05]: You know that.
[SPEAKER_05]: Colloquially, you already know that.
[SPEAKER_05]: Everybody knows that.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's just they don't have enough reasons, because they haven't recollected sufficiently enough of the dangers, the context, the benefits.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, they lack faith.
[SPEAKER_05]: They lack faith in sticking to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is that sutta I was mentioning?
[SPEAKER_05]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is the layman speaking to Venerable Ananda.
[SPEAKER_03]: It says, Bhante Ananda, we laymen enjoy essential pleasures, take delight in essential pleasures and rejoice in essential pleasures.
[SPEAKER_03]: Renunciation seems like a precipice to us.
[SPEAKER_03]: I have heard that in this dhamma and discipline there are very young
[SPEAKER_03]: Bhikkhus who, you know, go forth and delight in that renunciation.
[SPEAKER_03]: But how come my mind doesn't delight in it, even though I know, in theory, all this, the teaching already?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, anyway, there's a bit of a further discussion, but the Buddha says, before my enlightenment, while I was just a Bodhisatta, it occurred to me, good is renunciation, good is solitude, yet my mind did not launch out upon renunciation and become calm, settled and liberated in it, though I saw it as peaceful.
[SPEAKER_03]: It occurred to me, why is it that my mind does not launch out upon renunciation,
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, it occurred to me, I have not seen the danger in sensual pleasures and I have not cultivated that insight.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, that's even before he was enlightened.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: I have not thought about it.
[SPEAKER_03]: I have not achieved the benefit in renunciation and have not pursued it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Therefore, my mind does not launch out upon renunciation.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then,
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, later he says, if having seen the danger in sensual pleasures, I would cultivate that insight, and if having achieved the benefit in renunciation, I would pursue it, since it is peaceful.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sometime later, having seen the danger in sensual pleasures, I cultivated that insight.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, cultivate the insight.
[SPEAKER_05]: Recollect it, reflect on it.
[SPEAKER_05]: You get a degree of understanding, then cultivate that understanding further.
[SPEAKER_05]: So that's your meditation, that's your practice.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's not like mindlessly sitting and switching the thoughts off, and experiencing pleasant bodily sensations, and then waking up from it, and then not knowing how to deal with stuff when it starts to pressuring you, because you haven't dealt with anything.
[SPEAKER_05]: You're just shutting yourself down, because you don't want to deal with stuff.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's pretty much it.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that's completely the opposite of what the practice is.
[SPEAKER_05]: So reflect, recollect, sit down to meditate, quote-unquote, and by that I mean sit down and spend an hour, dedicated hour of your time, in like a motionless state of recollecting and reflecting and cultivating the insights of the danger, the peril, and when you get off your cushion, the danger, the traps, the baits will be all around you.
[SPEAKER_05]: And you will not go towards them, and you will maintain the context of the dissatisfaction, and the precipice, if you do, and all of that, and learn how to live among the bait, without touching the bait, like the deer herd sutta.
[SPEAKER_05]: You need to learn that.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's not magically going to be revealed and highlighted little markers around the bait.
[SPEAKER_05]: No.
[SPEAKER_05]: You need to discern that, and maintain that, and then you become comfortable within it.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then, obviously,
[SPEAKER_05]: Having not been trapped for a long time, you're going to develop even more confidence in it, because you are actually free.
[SPEAKER_05]: You can run in between the bait and you will not get caught.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's how confident you'll be.
[SPEAKER_05]: You won't need to shelter yourself in that sense.
[SPEAKER_05]: But that need... that takes work.
[SPEAKER_05]: Diligence, recollection, reflection, maintenance of the context and enduring of the pressure of acting out that you don't... don't give in to.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, and the sutta goes on.
[SPEAKER_03]: You see the danger in that sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: You cultivate that insight.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the further away, you obviously see something as dangerous.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're going to be moving away from it, dispassionate, not engaging.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that results in the first jhāna, the peace of renunciation.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, he's done nothing else.
[SPEAKER_04]: Except reflect... Where the baits are, where the traps are, and withdrawing himself from the traps.
[SPEAKER_05]: There is no... Well, I don't know what do I say, what should I say no to.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, because you haven't reflected on things long enough.
[SPEAKER_05]: If you do, it will become clearer.
[SPEAKER_05]: And there will be layers and layers that you can peel, until you specifically, directly recognize the roots of sensual desire.
[SPEAKER_05]: In the beginning, yeah, you maybe have to say no to too many things.
[SPEAKER_05]: Unnecessarily so.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it will cause you a bit more pain.
[SPEAKER_05]: But if you make the effort to reflect,
[SPEAKER_05]: Recollect.
[SPEAKER_05]: Cultivate those insights.
[SPEAKER_05]: It will crystallize more and more.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then, you realize, no, I can relax, actually.
[SPEAKER_05]: This is not dangerous.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's not dangerous.
[SPEAKER_05]: This is not rooted in sensuality.
[SPEAKER_05]: But, measure for that is the internal knowledge, not the external criteria or the word of another.
[SPEAKER_05]: Now, obviously, there are certain obvious things that are always rooted in sensuality.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, things basically, eh... against the precepts.
[SPEAKER_05]: And I mean, like, say, five precepts with the third precept being celibacy.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's kind of, you know, intoxication, lying, stealing and all of that.
[SPEAKER_05]: And sensual desire, distraction through your senses and sense objects, yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: So you need to say no to that, always, you know, like you can't go wrong there.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because more often than not, your intention will always be the root in sensuality when it comes to those things.
[SPEAKER_05]: But the cultivation needs to happen.
[SPEAKER_05]: Often, frequently reflecting...
[SPEAKER_03]: But just saying no to things...
[SPEAKER_00]: We're still desiring them.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_05]: People, you start by saying no to things, and what do you do then?
[SPEAKER_05]: Do you just hope now, that on account of your saying no, truth will become apparent?
[SPEAKER_05]: Or, have you, once you said no, are you now reflecting and recollecting and cultivating insights into danger, peril, so that you don't have to forcefully say no?
[SPEAKER_05]: You simply wouldn't want to go there, when you recognize the danger of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's funny, because maybe some people say, you know, the pleasure of jhāna will help you not go back to sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the common misconception.
[SPEAKER_05]: The insight of danger of sensuality will not make you go back to sensuality.
[SPEAKER_05]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that's the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is what the pleasure of it is.
[SPEAKER_05]: Which is what the pleasure of jhāna is, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like, this pleasure will surmount this joy and satisfaction.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, I'll get the pleasure so great, that I will not want any pleasure lesser than that.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, that's like, that's the definition of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's exactly like, let me just get this, and I'll never want anything else again.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's like every sensual desire.
[SPEAKER_04]: Doesn't matter how big or small it might be.
[SPEAKER_03]: And even in that same sutta, it says,
[SPEAKER_03]: He was thinking about second jhāna.
[SPEAKER_03]: And he understood.
[SPEAKER_03]: But why doesn't his mind launch out upon it and get there, yoniso?
[SPEAKER_03]: The same thing applies.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's because he was finding the light in that first jhāna, the thinking upon it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And once he saw that as an affliction, the danger in that...
[SPEAKER_05]: The danger, the obstacle, the lack of refinement, then, yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: When he withdrew himself from first jhāna into second.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, first jhāna is the withdrawal from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_05]: Second jhāna is withdrawal from the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_05]: Third jhāna is withdrawal from the second jhāna.
[SPEAKER_05]: Fourth jhāna is withdrawal from the third jhāna.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's not like, oh, I leap into it and then there's... No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_05]: By completely withdrawing, abandoning desire for this, removing any, any kind of affinity towards it, seeing the danger, the peril, the lack of satisfaction, that's how you enter the next one.
[SPEAKER_03]: I've seen the affliction of the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: And there's that sutta of the cow, the simile of the cow, where it steps on one stone and doesn't gain its balance and steadiness there, but it wants to step on the next one and then falls between the two.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's the same, like, somebody starts withdrawing from sensuality, sends the first jhāna, but then he wants the second jhāna, and then he gets neither.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, withdrawal from desires internally, externally, drying up.